Let me talk about India
اسمحوا لي أن أتحدث عن الهند
through the evolution of ideas.
من خلال تطور الأفكار
Now I believe this is an interesting way of looking at it
الآن أعتقد أن هذه طريقة جيدة للنظر إلى الأمور
because in every society, especially an open democratic society,
لأن في كل مجتمع، وخاصة في مجتمع ديمقراطي مفتوح
it's only when ideas take root that things change.
.الأمور تتغير فقط عندما تترسخ الأفكار
Slowly ideas lead to ideology,
،و شيئا فشيئا تتحول الأفكار إلى أيديولوجيا
lead to policies that lead to actions.
.تؤدي إلى سياسات تؤدي بدورها إلى اتخاذ إجراءات
In 1930 this country went through a Great Depression,
،في عام 1930 مر هذا البلد بكساد كبير
which led to all the ideas of the state and social security,
مما أضر بجميع أفكار الدولة والضمان الاجتماعي
and all the other things that happened in Roosevelt's time.
"وجميع الأشياء الأخرى التي وقعت في عهد "روزفلت
In the 1980s we had the Reagan revolution, which lead to deregulation.
في 1980 وقعت ثورة "ريغان" ، والتي أدت إلى رفع القيود.
And today, after the global economic crisis,
،واليوم وبعد الأزمة الاقتصادية العالمية
there was a whole new set of rules
كان هناك مجموعة جديدة كاملة من القواعد
about how the state should intervene.
حول الطريقة التي ينبغي للدولة أن تتدخل بها
So ideas change states.
فإمكان الأفكار أن تغيير الدول
And I looked at India and said,
:ونظرت إلى الهند ، وقلت
really there are four kinds of ideas
في الحقيقة هناك أربعة أنواع من الأفكار
which really make an impact on India.
والتي يمكن أن يكون لها بحق تأثير على الهند
The first, to my mind,
،الأول، في رأيي
is what I call as "the ideas that have arrived."
"هو ما أسميه "الأفكار الواردة
These ideas have brought together something
هذه الأفكار أدت مجتمعة
which has made India happen the way it is today.
إلى جعل الهند على النحو الذي هو عليه اليوم
The second set of ideas I call "ideas in progress."
"المجموعة الثانية من الأفكار أسميتها "أفكار بصدد التطور
Those are ideas which have been accepted
و هي تلك الأفكار التي تم قبولها
but not implemented yet.
ولكن لم تنفذ بعد
The third set of ideas are what I call as
المجموعة الثالثة من الأفكار هي ما أسميه
"ideas that we argue about" --
"الأفكار التي نتصارع من اجلها"
those are ideas where we have a fight,
أفكار لدينا فيها صراع
an ideological battle about how to do things.
صراع ايديولوجي حول كيفية عمل الاشياء
And the fourth thing, which I believe is most important, is
،والشيء الرابع ، وهو باعتقادي الأكثر أهمية
"the ideas that we need to anticipate."
"الأفكار التي علينا أن نتوقعها"
Because when you are a developing country
لأنه إذا كنت أحد البلدان النامية
in the world where you can see the problems that other countries are having,
بإمكانك أن ترى في العالم من حولك ما تواجهه بلدان أخرى من مشاكل
you can actually anticipate
و يكون بامكانك أن تتوقع
what that did and do things very differently.
بناءا على ما فعلوا هم وتتصرف انت بطريقة مختلفة جدا
Now in India's case I believe there are six ideas
الآن في حالة الهند أعتقد أن هناك ستة أفكار
which are responsible for where it has come today.
أدت إلى ما أصبح عليه اليوم
The first is really the notion of people.
الأولى هو في الحقيقة نظرتنا للشعب
In the '60s and '70s
في الستينيات و السبعينيات
we thought of people as a burden.
كنا ننظر للشعب على انه عبئ
We thought of people as a liability.
كنا نعتقد أن الشعب مسؤولية
Today we talk of people as an asset.
اليوم نعتبر أن الشعب هو الأساس
We talk of people as human capital.
نتكلم عن الشعب باعتباره رأس مال بشري
And I believe this change in the mindset,
وأعتقد أن هذا التغيير في العقلية
of looking at people as something of a burden
من النظر إلى الشعب على أنه عبء
to human capital,
إلى اعتباره رأس مال بشري
has been one of the fundamental changes in the Indian mindset.
مثل احد التغيرات الأساسية في الفكر الهندي
And this change in thinking of human capital
وهذا التغيير في التفكير في رأس المال البشري
is linked to the fact
مرتبط بحقيقة أن
that India is going through a demographic dividend.
الهند تبنت خيار الديمقراطية
As healthcare improves,
و مع تحسن الرعاية الصحية
as infant mortality goes down,
وانخفاض معدل وفيات الاطفال
fertility rates start dropping. And India is experiencing that.
معدلات الخصوبة بدأت في الانخفاض, وتتعامل الهند مع هذا
India is going to have
الهند سيكون لديها
a lot of young people with a demographic dividend
الكثير من الشباب في العائد الديموغرافي
for the next 30 years.
لمدة 30 عاما القادمة
What is unique about this demographic dividend
وما هو فريد بالنسبة لهذا العائد الديموغرافي
is that India will be the only country in the world
هو ان الهند ستكون الدولة الوحيدة في العالم
to have this demographic dividend.
التي تتمتع بهذا العائد الديموغرافي
In other words, it will be the only young country in an aging world.
وبعبارة أخرى ، سيكون البلد الشاب الوحيد في عالم مسن
And this is very important. At the same time
وهذا أمر هام جدا. في الوقت نفسه
if you peel away the demographic dividend in India,
إذا أمعنا النظر في العائد الديموغرافي في الهند
there are actually two demographic curves.
هناك حاليا منحنيين ديموغرافيين اثنين
One is in the south and in the west of India,
،واحد في جنوب وغرب الهند
which is already going to be fully expensed by 2015,
وهو ما سينتشر بالكامل بحلول عام 2015
because in that part of the country, the fertility rate is
فمعدل الخصوبة في ذلك الجزء من البلاد
almost equal to that of a West European country.
تكاد تساوي معدل الخصوبة في غرب أوروبا
Then there is the whole northern India,
ثم هناك كامل شمال الهند
which is going to be the bulk of the future demographic dividend.
والذي سيمثل الجزء الأكبر من العائد الديموغرافي في المستقبل
But a demographic dividend is only as good
ولكن العائد الديموغرافي هو جيد
as the investment in your human capital.
بقدر الاستثمار في رأس المال البشري
Only if the people have education,
،فقط إذا كان للناس الحق في التعليم
they have good health, they have infrastructure,
و كانوا بصحة جيدة ،و لديهم بنية تحتية
they have roads to go to work, they have lights to study at night --
لديهم طرق للذهاب الى العمل، لديهم إنارة تمكنهم من الدراسة ليلا
only in those cases can you really get the benefit
فقط في هذه الحالات يمكن أن تحصل على نتيجة
of a demographic dividend.
لهذا العائد الديموغرافي
In other words, if you don't really invest in the human capital,
وبعبارة أخرى، إذا لم يكن استثمارك في رأس المال البشري
the same demographic dividend
نفس العائد الديموغرافي
can be a demographic disaster.
يمكن ان يكون كارثة ديموغرافية
Therefore India is at a critical point
اذا الهند في مرحلة حرجة
where either it can leverage its demographic dividend
حيث يمكن لها ان تنهض بفضل هذا العائد الديموغرافي
or it can lead to a demographic disaster.
أو أن ينتهي بها الامر إلى كارثة ديموغرافية
The second thing in India has been the change in
الأمر الثاني في الهند الذي قد تغير
the role of entrepreneurs.
دور رجال الأعمال
When India got independence entrepreneurs were seen
عندما حصلت الهند على الاستقلال اعتبر رجال الأعمال
as a bad lot, as people who would exploit.
كحفنة سيئة،كأناس مستغلين
But today, after 60 years, because of the rise of entrepreneurship,
ولكن اليوم وبعد 60 عاما، وبسبب ارتفاع روح المبادرة
entrepreneurs have become role models,
تحول أصحاب المشاريع إلى قدوة
and they are contributing hugely to the society.
وهم يسهمون بشكل كبير في بناء المجتمع
This change has contributed
وقد ساهم هذا التحول
to the vitality and the whole economy.
في إضفاء حيوية على الاقتصاد ككل
The third big thing I believe that has changed India
الأمر المهم الثالث و الذي أعتقد أنه غير الهند
is our attitude towards the English language.
هو موقفنا من اللغة الانجليزية
English language was seen as a language of the imperialists.
اللغة الانجليزية كان ينظر اليها على انها لغة الامبرياليين
But today, with globalization,
ولكن اليوم مع العولمة
with outsourcing, English has become a language of aspiration.
مع الاستعانة بمصادر خارجية ، الانجليزية أصبحت لغة إلهام
This has made it something that everybody wants to learn.
هذا ما جعل الكل يريد أن يتعلمها
And the fact that we have English is now becoming
وفي الواقع اصبحت الانجليزية الآن
a huge strategic asset.
قاعدة استراتيجية ضخمة
The next thing is technology.
الشيء التالي هو التكنولوجيا
Forty years back, computers were seen
منذ 40 سنة،اعتبرت الحواسيب
as something which was forbidding, something which was intimidating,
أمرا ممنوعا،أمرا محرجا
something that reduced jobs.
أمرا سيؤدي إلى خفض الوظائف
Today we live in a country
اليوم نحن نعيش في بلد
which sells eight million mobile phones a month,
تباع فيه شهريا ثمانية ملايين هاتفا نقالا
of which 90 percent of those mobile phones
تسعون في المئة من تلك الهواتف النقالة
are prepaid phones
هي هواتف مدفوعة مسبقا
because people don't have credit history.
لأن الناس ليس لديهم سجل ائتماني
Forty percent of those prepaid phones
اربعون في المئة من هذه الهواتف المدفوعة مسبقا
are recharged at less than 20 cents at each recharge.
تكلفة إعادة شحنها ليس أقل من 20 سنتا لكل عملية شحن
That is the scale at which
إلى هذا الحد تمكنت
technology has liberated and made it accessible.
التكنولوجيا إلى تحريره وجعله في المتناول
And therefore technology has gone
وهكذا تحولت التكنولوجيا
from being seen as something forbidding
من شيء ينظر إليه على أنه ممنوع
and intimidating to something that is empowering.
ومحرج إلى شيء يزيد في القوة
Twenty years back,
منذ 20 سنة
when there was a report on bank computerization,
عندما كانت تحرر تقارير الحوسبة البنكية
they didn't name the report as
لم يكونوا يسمون التقرير
a report on computers,
تقرير على الكمبيوتر
they call them as "ledger posting machines."
كانوا يسمونهم آلات نشر الدفاتر
They didn't want the unions to believe that they were actually computers.
لانهم لم يكونوا يريدون ان تعلم النقابات انهم يستعملون فعلا الكمبيوتر
And when they wanted to have more advanced, more powerful computers
وعندما أرادوا أن تكون لهم أجهزة كمبيوتر أكثر تطورا وأقوى
they called them "advanced ledger posting machines."
أسموها آلات نشر دفاتر متطورة
So we have come a long way from those days
لذلك يمكن القول أننا قطعنا شوطا مهما منذ تلك الأيام
where the telephone has become an instrument of empowerment,
حيث أصبح الهاتف أداة للتمكين
and really has changed the way Indians think of technology.
وبالفعل تغيرت نظرة الهنود للتكنولوجيا
And then I think the other point
واعتقد ان النقطة الأخرى
is that Indians today are far more
هو أن الهنود اليوم هم أكثر
comfortable with globalization.
رفاهية مع قدوم العولمة
Again, after having lived for more than 200 years
مرة أخرى، بعد أن عاش لأكثر من 200 سنة
under the East India Company and under imperial rule,
في إطار شركة الهند الشرقية، وتحت الحكم الامبريالي
Indians had a very natural reaction towards globalization
كان للهنود رد فعل طبيعي جدا نحو العولمة
believing it was a form of imperialism.
معتبرين اياه شكل من أشكال الإمبريالية
But today, as Indian companies go abroad,
ولكن اليوم، و بما أن الشركات الهندية عبرت الحدود الى الخارج
as Indians come and work all over the world,
كما ان الهنود أصبح بإمكانهم العمل في جميع أنحاء العالم
Indians have gained a lot more confidence
اكتسب الهنود المزيد من الثقة
and have realized that globalization is something they can participate in.
وأدركوا أن العولمة هو شيء بإمكانهم المشاركة فيه
And the fact that the demographics are in our favor,
وحقيقة أن التركيبة السكانية في صالحنا
because we are the only young country in an aging world,
بما أننا البلد الوحيد الشاب في عالم مسن
makes globalization all the more attractive to Indians.
جعلت العولمة أكثر جاذبية للهنود
And finally, India has had
وأخيرا تمكنت الهند
the deepening of its democracy.
من ترسيخ الديمقراطية
When democracy came to India 60 years back
عندما أتت الديمقراطية إلى الهند قبل 60 سنة
it was an elite concept.
كانت مفهوما نخبويا
It was a bunch of people who wanted to bring in democracy
حفنة من الأشخاص كانوا يريدون الانخراط في مسار ديمقراطي
because they wanted to bring in the idea of
لأنهم يريدون ترسيخ فكرة
universal voting and parliament and constitution and so forth.
التصويت والبرلمان والدستور، وهلم جرا
But today democracy has become a bottom-up process
ولكن الديمقراطية أصبحت اليوم عملية تبدأ من القاعدة
where everybody has realized
حيث أدرك الجميع
the benefits of having a voice,
فائدة أن يكون له صوت
the benefits of being in an open society.
فائدة أن يكون في مجتمع مفتوح
And therefore democracy has become embedded.
وبالتالي ، أصبح جزءا لا يتجزأ من الديمقراطية
I believe these six factors --
وأعتقد أن هذه العوامل الستة
the rise of the notion of population as human capital,
صعود مفهوم السكان على أساس رأس مال بشري
the rise of Indian entrepreneurs,
صعود رجال الأعمال الهنود
the rise of English as a language of aspiration,
اعتبار الانجليزية لغة إلهام
technology as something empowering,
اعتبار التكنولوجيا وسيلة للتطور
globalization as a positive factor,
والعولمة بوصفها عاملا إيجابيا
and the deepening of democracy -- has contributed
وتعميق الديمقراطية قد أسهمت
to why India is today growing
في تطور الهند اليوم
at rates it has never seen before.
بمعدلات لم تشهدها من قبل
But having said that,
و بعد قول هذا
then we come to what I call as ideas in progress.
"نأتي إلى ما أسميته "فكرة بصدد التطور
Those are the ideas where there is no argument in a society,
وهي تلك الأفكار التي لا يوجد للمجتمع عليها اعتراض
but you are not able to implement those things.
ولكنك لا تستطيع أن تنفيذها
And really there are four things here.
والواقع أن هناك أربعة أمور هنا
One is the question of education.
واحدة هي مسألة التعليم
For some reason, whatever reason -- lack of money,
لسبب ما ، وأيا كانت الأسباب ، عدم وجود أموال
lack of priorities, because of religion having an older culture --
عدم وجود أولويات ، وذلك بسبب وجود الدين بثقافته القديمة
primary education was never given the focus it required.
لم يحضا التعليم الابتدائي بالاهتمام الذي يستحقه
But now I believe it's reached a point
ولكن أعتقد أنه وصل الآن إلى نقطة
where it has become very important.
حيث أصبح على جانب من الأهمية
Unfortunately the government schools don't function,
ومما يؤسف له أن المدرسة الحكومية لا تعمل
so children are going to private schools today.
لذلك يرتاد الأطفال اليوم المدارس الخاصة
Even in the slums of India
وحتى في الأحياء الفقيرة في الهند
more than 50 percent of urban kids are going into private schools.
أكثر من 50% من أطفال المناطق الحضرية يرتادون مدارس خاصة
So there is a big challenge in getting the schools to work.
ذلك أن هناك تحديا كبيرا لارتياد المدارس للحصول على وضيفة
But having said that, there is an enormous desire
بعد قول هذا يمكن التأكيد أن هناك رغبة كبيرة
among everybody, including the poor, to educate their children.
بين الجميع، بمن فيهم الفقراء، لتعليم أطفالهم
So I believe primary education is an idea
لذا أعتقد أن التعليم الابتدائي فكرة واردة
which is arrived but not yet implemented.
لكنها لم تنفذ بعد
Similarly, infrastructure --
الشيء نفسه ينطبق على البنية التحتية
for a long time, infrastructure was not a priority.
لزمن طويل لم تكن البنية التحتية تمثل أولوية
Those of you who have been to India have seen that.
ومن كان منكم في الهند شاهد ذلك
It's certainly not like China.
انها بالتأكيد ليست مثل الصين
But today I believe finally infrastructure is something
لكن الان اعتقد ان الجميع متفق ان البنية التحتية
which is agreed upon and which people want to implement.
هو شيء يجب انجازه
It is reflected in the political statements.
وهذا ما نراه في التصريحات السياسية
20 years back the political slogan was, "Roti, kapada, makaan,"
"منذ 20 سنة كان الشعار السياسي "روتي, كابرا, مكان
which meant, "Food, clothing and shelter."
"وهو ما يعني "الغذاء ,الكساء ,المأوى
And today's political slogan is, "Bijli, sadak, pani,"
"أمااليوم فالشعار السياسي هو "بجلي, سراك, باني
which means "Electricity, water and roads."
"وهو ما يعني "الكهرباء, والمياه, والطرق
And that is a change in the mindset
و يعتبر هذا تغيرا في العقلية
where infrastructure is now accepted.
حيث أصبحت البنية التحتية الآن مقبولة
So I do believe this is an idea which has arrived,
لذا اعتقد أن هذه فكرة واردة
but simply not implemented.
ولكن ببساطة لم تنفذ
The third thing is again cities.
الأمر الثالث هو من جديد المدن
It's because Gandhi believed in villages
لأن غاندي كان يؤمن بالقرى
and because the British ruled from the cities,
ولأن البريطانيين حكموا من المدن
therefore Nehru thought of New Delhi as an un-Indian city.
ولذلك و بالرغم من أن نهرو رأى في نيودلهي مدينة هندية
For a long time we have neglected our cities.
ظلت مدننا ولفترة طويلة مهملة
And that is reflected in the kinds of situations that you see.
وهذا ما يتجلى في الوضعيات التي ترونها
But today, finally, after economic reforms,
ولكن أخيرا اليوم و بعد الإصلاحات الاقتصادية
and economic growth,
والنمو الاقتصادي
I think the notion that cities are engines
أعتقد أن فكرة أن المدن هي محركات
of economic growth,
النمو الاقتصادي
cities are engines of creativity,
المدن هي محركات للإبداع
cities are engines of innovation,
المدن هي محركات للابتكار
have finally been accepted.
تم قبولها أخيرا
And I think now you're seeing the move towards improving our cities.
واعتقد انه بإمكانكم رؤية التحرك من اجل تحسين مدننا
Again, an idea which is arrived, but not yet implemented.
من جديد هذه فكرة وردت لكنها لم تنفذ بعد
The final thing is the notion of India as a single market --
الأمر الأخير هو مفهوم أن الهند تمثل سوقا واحدة
because when you didn't think of India as a market,
لأنه إذا لم تعتبر بأن الهند سوق
you didn't really bother about a single market, because it didn't really matter.
لن تهتم حقا بأنها سوق واحدة
And therefore you had a situation
ولذلك ستجد نفسك في وضع
where every state had its own market for products.
حيث كل ولاية لديها سوق منتجات خاص بها
Every province had its own market for agriculture.
كل مقاطعة لديها سوق منتجات زراعية خاص بها
Increasingly now the policies of
تتزايد الآن سياسات
taxation and infrastructure and all that,
الضرائب والبنية التحتية وكل ذلك
are moving towards creating India as a single market.
يتجه نحو جعل الهند سوق واحدة
So there is a form of internal globalization which is happening,
ولذلك يمكن اعتبار الذي حدث شكلا من أشكال العولمة الداخلي
which is as important as external globalization.
والذي لا يقل أهمية عن العولمة الخارجية
These four factors I believe --
هذه العوامل الأربعة في اعتقادي
the ones of primary education,
وهي التعليم الابتدائي
infrastructure, urbanization, and single market --
البنية التحتية والتوسع الحضري والسوق الموحدة
in my view are ideas in India
في رأيي هي أفكار في الهند
which have been accepted, but not implemented.
تم قبولها ولكنها لم تنفذ
Then we have what I believe are the ideas in conflict.
ثم لدينا ما أعتقد أنها أفكار متصارعة
The ideas that we argue about.
الأفكار التي نتصارع من اجلها
These are the arguments we have which cause gridlock.
وهذه هي الحجج التي لدينا والتي تتسبب في جمود
What are those ideas? One is, I think, are ideological issues.
ما هي هذه الأفكار؟ أولا أعتقد أنها قضايانا الأيديولوجية
Because of the historical Indian background, in the caste system,
نظرا للخلفية التاريخية الهندية ونظام الطبقات
and because of the fact that there have been many people
ونظرا لأن هنالك الكثير من الناس
who have been left out in the cold,
الذين تم تركهم في العراء
a lot of the politics is about how to make sure
الكثير من السياسات تعمل من اجل التأكد
that we'll address that.
ان هذا الأمر ستتم معالجته
And it leads to reservations and other techniques.
ويؤدي هذا إلى تحفظات وغيرها من التقنيات
It's also related to the way that we subsidize our people,
كما أنها تتعلق بالأسلوب الذي ندعم الشعب به
and all the left and right arguments that we have.
وبجميع حجج اليمين واليسار التي لدينا
A lot of the Indian problems are related to the ideology
الكثير من المشاكل لدا الهنود متعلقة بالأيديولوجية
of caste and other things.
الطبقية وغيرها من الأمور
This policy is causing gridlock.
وهذه السياسة تؤدي إلى جمود
This is one of the factors which needs to be resolved.
هذا هو أحد العوامل الذي يحتاج إلى حل
The second one is the labor policies that we have,
والثاني هو أن سياسات العمالة لدينا
which make it so difficult for
وهو ما جعل الامر صعبا على
entrepreneurs to create standardized jobs in companies,
أصحاب المشاريع لخلق فرص عمل في الشركات
that 93 percent of Indian labor
إن 93 في المائة من العمال الهنود
is in the unorganized sector.
ينتمون إلى قطاع غير منظم
They have no benefits: they don't have social security;
وليس لديهم أي منح و ليس لديهم ضمان الاجتماعي
they don't have pension; they don't have healthcare; none of those things.
ليس لديهم معاش وليس لهم الرعاية الصحية أو أيا من تلك الأشياء
This needs to be fixed because unless you can bring these people
هذا يحتاج إلى إصلاح لأنه ما لم تستطع أن تبدل هؤلاء الناس
into the formal workforce,
إلى عمالة رسمية
you will end up creating a whole lot of people who are completely disenfranchised.
فسينتهي الأمر برمته إلى خلق أناس كثيرين محرومين تماما
Therefore we need to create a new set of labor laws,
لذلك نحن بحاجة لخلق مجموعة جديدة من قوانين العمل
which are not as onerous as they are today.
وهي ليست باهظة مثلما هي اليوم
At the same time give a policy for a lot more people to be in the formal sector,
في الوقت ذاته الضمان للكثير من الناس أن يكونوا في القطاع الرسمي
and create the jobs for the millions of people that we need to create jobs for.
وخلق فرص عمل للملايين من الناس ممن نحن بحاجة لخلق فرص عمل لهم
The third thing is our higher education.
الشيء الثالث هو تعليمنا العالي
Indian higher education is completely regulated.
التعليم العالي الهندي نظامي صرف
It's very difficult to start a private university.
ومن الصعب جدا أن تنشأ جامعة خاصة
It's very difficult for a foreign university to come to India.
ومن الصعب جدا للجامعات الأجنبية القدوم إلى الهند
As a result of that our higher education
نتيجة لذلك تعليمنا العالي
is simply not keeping pace with India's demands.
وببساطة لم يواكب المطالب الهندية
That is leading to a lot of problems which we need to address.
و من شأن هذا أن يؤدي إلى الكثير من المشاكل التي يتعين علينا التصدي لها
But most important I believe
ولكن أعتقد أن الأكثر أهمية
are the ideas we need to anticipate.
هي الأفكار التي يتعين علينا توقعها
Here India can look at what is happening in the west
هنا يمكن للهند أن تنظر إلى ما يحدث في الغرب
and elsewhere, and look at what needs to be done.
وفي أماكن أخرى والنظر في ما ينبغي عمله
The first thing is, we're very fortunate
أول شيء هو ونحن محظوظون للغاية
that technology is at a point
ان التكنولوجيا وصلت الى حد
where it is much more advanced
بحيث أنها باتت أكثر تقدما
than when other countries had the development.
مما كانت عليه عندما كانت بلدان أخرى بصدد التطور
So we can use technology for governance.
أصبح بإمكاننا إذا استخدام هذه التكنولوجيا للتحكم
We can use technology for direct benefits.
يمكننا استخدام التكنولوجيا من أجل تحقيق منافع مباشرة
We can use technology for transparency, and many other things.
نستطيع استخدام التكنولوجيا لأغراض الشفافية وأشياء أخرى كثيرة
The second thing is, the health issue.
الشيء الثاني هو المسألة الصحية
India has equally horrible
فالهند لديها أيضا
health problems of the higher state of cardiac issue,
مشاكل صحية كارتفاع حالات أمراض القلب
the higher state of diabetes, the higher state of obesity.
ارتفاع حالات أمراض السكري و أمراض السمنة المفرطة
So there is no point in replacing a set of poor country diseases
ولذلك لا فائدة من مقارنة أمراض بلدان فقيرة
with a set of rich country diseases.
مع أمراض بلدان غنية
Therefore we're to rethink the whole way we look at health.
ولذلك علينا إعادة التفكير في طريقة نظرنا الى المسائل الصحية
We really need to put in place a strategy
يتعين علينا ان نضع استراتيجية
so that we don't go to the other extreme of health.
حتى لا ننتقل إلى الطرف الآخر للصحة
Similarly today in the West
وكذلك الأمر اليوم في الغرب
you're seeing the problem of entitlement --
ترون مشكلة الاستحقاق
the cost of social security, the cost of Medicare, the cost of Medicaid.
تكاليف الضمان الاجتماعي وتكاليف الرعاية الطبية وتكاليف المساعدة الطبية
Therefore when you are a young country,
ولذلك عندما تكون دولة شابة
again you have a chance to put in place a modern pension system
تجد مجددا فرصة لتضع نظام معاشات تقاعدية حديثا
so that you don't create entitlement problems as you grow old.
حتى لا تخلق مشاكل الحقوق كلما تقدمتم في السن
And then again, India does not have the luxury
ومرة أخرى الهند لا تملك ترف
of making its environment dirty,
جعل بيئتها قذرة
because it has to marry environment and development.
لأنه عليها الجمع بين البيئة والتنمية
Just to give an idea, the world has to stabilize
فقط لإعطاء فكرة عن ذلك على العالم الاستقرار في مستوى
at something like 20 gigatons per year.
عشرون جيجا طن أو نحو ذلك في السنة
On a population of nine billion
لما يبلغ تسعة مليارات نسمة
our average carbon emission will have to be about two tons per year.
متوسط انبعاث الكربون لدينا يجب أن يكون نحو طنين سنويا
India is already at two tons per year.
الانبعاثات حاليا في الهند تبلغ طنين اثنين سنويا
But if India grows at something like eight percent,
ولكن إذا نمت الهند بما يعادل ثمانية في المائة
income per year per person will go to 16 times by 2050.
فان دخل الفرد الواحد في السنة سيتضاعف 16 مرة بحلول عام 2050
So we're saying: income growing at 16 times and no growth in carbon.
نحن نريد زيادة في الدخل تبلغ 16 مرة بدون أي زيادة في انبعاث الكربون
Therefore we will fundamentally rethink the way we look at the environment,
ولذلك علينا أن نعيد التفكير جوهريا بالطريقة تعاطينا مع البيئة
the way we look at energy,
الطريقة تعاطينا مع الطاقة
the way we create whole new paradigms of development.
طريقة جديدة لتشكيل نماذج متكاملة للتنمية
Now why does this matter to you?
و لكن ما الذي يجعل هذه المسألة مهمة بالنسبة لكم؟
Why does what's happening 10 thousand miles away matter to all of you?
ما الذي يجعل ما يحدث على بعد 10 آلاف ميل أمرا مها لكم جميعا؟
Number one, this matters because
هذه مسألة مهمة أولا لان
this represents more than a billion people.
هذا الأمر يهم أكثر من مليار نسمة
A billion people, 1/6th of the world population.
مليار نسمة تمثل سدس سكان العالم
It matters because this is a democracy.
هذه مسألة مهمة لأنها تخص دولة ديمقراطية
And it is important to prove
ومن المهم أن نثبت
that growth and democracy are not incompatible,
ان النمو والديمقراطية لا يتعارضان
that you can have a democracy, that you can have an open society,
وأنه يمكن أن تكون ديمقراطيا وأن يكون لديك مجتمع منفتح
and you can have growth.
وان تتمكن من تحقيق نمو
It's important because if you solve these problems,
و هذا أمر مهم لأنه إذا حلت هذه المشاكل
you can solve the problems of poverty in the world.
يمكنك حل مشاكل الفقر في العالم
It's important because
و هذا أمر مهم لأنك
you need it to solve the world's environment problems.
تحتاج إليه لحل مشاكل البيئة في العالم
If we really want to come to a point,
وإذا كنا نريد حقا الوصول إلى هذه النقطة
we really want to put a cap on our carbon emission,
نريد أن نضع حدا أقصى لانبعاث الكربون
we want to really lower the use of energy --
نريد خفض استخدام الطاقة
it has to be solved in countries like India.
فلا بد من حل هذه المسألة في دول مثل الهند
You know if you look at the development
إذا نظرتم إلى التطور
in the West over 200 years,
الذي حصل في الغرب طوال أكثر من 200 سنة
the average growth may have been about two percent.
كان معدل النمو نحو اثنين في المئة
Here we are talking about countries growing at eight to nine percent.
بينما نحن هنا نتحدث عن بلدان تنمو بين ثمانية الى تسعة في المئة
And that makes a huge difference.
وهذا ما يجعل الفرق كبيرا
When India was growing at about three, 3.5 percent
عندما كانت الهند تنمو نحو 3.5 في المئة
and the population was growing at two percent,
وكان عدد السكان ينمو بمعدل 2 في المئة
its per capita income was doubling every 45 years.
كان نصيب الفرد من الدخل يتضاعف كل 45 سنة
When the economic growth goes to eight percent
عندما يصل النمو الاقتصادي الى ثمانية في المئة
and population growth drops to 1.5 percent,
والنمو السكاني ينخفض إلى 1.5 في المئة
then per capita income is doubling every nine years.
فان دخل الفرد يتضاعف كل تسع سنوات
In other words, you're certainly fast-forwarding this whole process
وبعبارة أخرى سوف تعجلون بالتأكيد عملية وصول
of a billion people going to prosperity.
مليار شخص الى الازدهار
And you must have a clear strategy
لذلك يجب أن تكون لديك إستراتيجية واضحة
which is important for India and important for the world.
وهو أمر هام بالنسبة للهند و بالنسبة للعالم
That is why I think all of you
وهذا ما يجعلني أعتقد أنكم جميعا
should be equally concerned with it as I am.
ينبغي أن تكونوا أيضا مثلي معنيين بهذا الامر
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)